Last updated: 18. Jan 2020

Elisa Filevich

Bernstein Center for Computational Neuroscience

Philippstr. 13 Haus 6 10115 Berlin Berlin, Germany Tel +49 30 2093 6313 elisa.filevich@bccn-berlin.de

Junior Group Leader http://metamotorlab.filevich.com

Research Profile

I am a cognitive neuroscientist investigating the neural correlates of consciousness. I focus on different aspects of motor awareness and subjective experiences associated with it: the awareness of intentions (volition), the awareness of control (agency) and motor experience (motor metacognition).

Academic Appointments

2017 - now	Junior Group Leader - Funded by "Freigeist" Fellowship Bernstein Center for Computational Neuroscience and Institute of Psychology, Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin, Germany.
2015 - 2017	Scientific employee (Seminar instructor)
	Faculty of Sports Sciences, Leipzig University, Germany.
	Guest Researcher
	Max Planck Institute for Human Development, Berlin, Germany.
2012 - 2015	Postdoctoral fellow. Structural Plasticity group
	Max Planck Institute, Berlin, Germany
	Team Leader: Dr. Simone Kühn

Education and Training

2008 - 2012	PhD. Institute of Cognitive Neuroscience. Intentional inhibition and human voluntary action. University College London. UK Advisor: Prof. Patrick Haggard
2012	Visiting Scholar. Consciousness and Computation Laboratory Columbia University, NY, USA Advisor: Asst. Prof. Hakwan Lau
2005 - 2007	Undergraduate researcher. Laboratory of Molecular and Cellular Biology (LBMC). University of Buenos Aires, Argentina Advisor: Prof. Osvaldo D. Uchitel
2005	Undergraduate researcher. Biochemistry and Molecular Biology. Colorado State University, CO, USA Advisor: Prof. James Bamburg
2001 – 2007	Licenciatura (equivalent to German "Diplom") in Biological Sciences. University of Buenos Aires, Argentina. Final grade: 8.6/10

Awards, Fellowships, and Research Gran	Awards	Fellowships	s, and Researd	:h Grants
--	--------	-------------	----------------	-----------

2018	Research Training Group (RTG). Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) RTG 2386 "Extrospection". Role: Principal Investigator. Total funding for the cluster of 10 Principal Investigators: over 1.530.000 €
2016	Freigeist Fellowship . VolkswagenStiftung, Germany. Grant number 91620, 5 years, 919800 €
2008	Four-year PhD Studentship in Neuroscience. Wellcome Trust, UK. Grant number 086123/Z/08/Z, 4 years, over 120000 GBP
2008	Overseas Research Scholarships (ORS). Higher Education Funding Council for England (HEFCE). Fee funding to cover the difference between Overseas and UK/EU tuition fees.
2006	Undergraduate scholarship. ("Beca estímulo") University of Buenos Aires, Argentina.

Pre-prints

2019

Filevich, E., Koß, C., & Faivre, N. Response-related signals increase confidence but not metacognitive performance. BioRxiv, 735712. https://doi.org/10.1101/735712

Publications in Peer-Reviewed Journals

Total number of peer-reviewed publications: 16

h-index: 11

Total number of citations (source: Google Scholar): 491		
2020	Filevich , E., Forlim, C. G., Fehrman, C., Forster, C., Paulus, M., Shing, Y. L., & Kühn, S. (2020). I know that I know nothing: Cortical thickness and functional connectivity underlying meta-ignorance ability in pre-schoolers. <i>Developmental Cognitive Neuroscience</i> , 41, 100738.	
	Rahnev, D., Desender, K., Lee, A.L.F., Adler, W.T., Aguilar-Lleyda, D., Akdoğan, B.,, Zylberberg, A. (2020) The Confidence Database. <i>Nat Hum Behav. In Press</i>	
2019	Karch, J. D., Filevich, E ., Wenger, E., Lisofsky, N., Becker, M., Butler, O., Kühn, S. (2019). Identifying predictors of within-person variance in MRI-based brain volume estimates. <i>NeuroImage</i> , 200, 575–589.	
2018	Faivre, N., Filevich, E. , Solovey, G., Kühn, S., Blanke, O. Behavioural, modeling, and electrophysiological evidence for domain-generality in human metacognition. <i>The Journal of Neuroscience</i> , 0322–17.	
2017	Filevich, E.* , Horn, S. S*., & Kühn, S. Within-person adaptivity in frugal judgments from memory. <i>Psychological Research</i> 83 (3), 613-630	
	Filevich E.*, Lisofsky, N.*, Becker, M., Butler, O., Lochstet, M., Martensson, J.,	

Wenger, E., Lindenberger, U. and Kühn, S. Day2day: Investigating daily variability of magnetic resonance imaging measures over half a year. BMC Neuroscience, 18:65.

^{*} Indicates equal contributions

Pannunzi, M., Hindriks, R., Bettinardi, R. G., Wenger, E., Lisofsky, N., Martensson, J., Butler, O., **Filevich, E**., Becker, M., Lochstet, M., Kühn S., Deco, G. Resting-state fMRI correlations: from link-wise unreliability to whole brain stability. *NeuroImage* 157:250-262

Filevich, E., Becker, M., Wu, YH. & Kühn, S. Seeing double: Exploring the phenomenology of self-reported absence of rivalry in bistable pictures. *Frontiers in Human Neuroscience* 11:301.

2015

Lange, K., Kühn, S., **Filevich, E**., "Just another tool for online studies" (JATOS): An easy solution for setup and management of web servers supporting online studies. *PLoS one*, 10(6).

Filevich, E., Dresler, M., Brick, T. R., & Kühn, S. Metacognitive mechanisms underlying lucid dreaming. *The Journal of Neuroscience*, 35(3), 1082–1088.

2013

Filevich, E., Vanneste, P., Brass, M., Fias, W., Haggard, P. Kühn, S. Brain correlates of subjective freedom of choice. *Consciousness and Cognition* 22 (4), 1271-1284

Filevich, E., & Haggard, P. Persistence of internal representations of alternative voluntary actions. *Frontiers in Cognition*, 4: 202.

Filevich, E., Kühn, S., & Haggard, P. There is no free won't: Antecedent brain activity predicts decisions to inhibit. *PLoS one*, 8(2), e53053.

2012

Filevich, E., Haggard, P. Grin and bear it! Neural consequences of a voluntary decision to act or inhibit action. *Experimental Brain Research*, 223(3), 341–351.

Filevich, E., Kühn, S., Haggard, P. Negative Motor Phenomena in cortical stimulation: implications for inhibitory control of human action. *Cortex* 48(10), 1251-1261

Filevich, E.*, Kühn, S.*, Haggard, P. Intentional inhibition in human action: The power of "no." *Neuroscience and Biobehavioral Reviews*, 36(4), 1107–1118.

Book Chapters

2014

Chambon, V. **Filevich, E.** Haggard, P. What is the human sense of agency, and is it metacognitive? In Stephen M. Fleming and Chris Frith (Eds). The cognitive neuroscience of metacognition. Springer

2012

Filevich, E. Haggard, P. Components of voluntary action. In Hallett, M., Lang, A. E., Jankovic, J., Fahn, S., Halligan, P. W., Voon, V., & Cloninger, C. R. (Eds.). Psychogenic Movement Disorders and Other Conversion Disorders. Cambridge University Press.

Invited	Tall	ks
IIIVILEG	Iaii	~3

2020	LPC Lab Seminar, Aix-Marseille Université. Motor Metacognition: How much does our brain know about the way it moves the body?
2019	Workshop on Metacognition. Laboratoire de Psychologie et NeuroCognition (LPNC), Grenoble, France. Motor metacognition: How does our brain know how our body moves? Freie Universität Berlin - CCNB Seminar Series. Germany. Relationships between domains of metacognitive monitoring
2018	Department of Experimental Psychology (Zangwill Club), Cambridge University, UK. Metacognition of internally generated processes
2017	Geneva University (Brain and Cognition Seminar), Switzerland. Metacognition of internally generated processes
	Experimental Psychology Society (EPS) Meeting, Belfast, UK. Domaingenerality in perceptual metacognition
2014	Department of Psychology, Lund University, Sweden. What we can learn from introspection

Presentations in Conferences		
2019	Association for the Scientific Study of Consciousness (ASSC23), London, Canada. Metacognitive access to high- and low-level aspects of motor control. (Plenary Symposium)	
2018	Association for the Scientific Study of Consciousness (ASSC22), Cracow, Poland. The brain basis of meta-ignorance in pre-schoolers	
2017	Association for the Scientific Study of Consciousness (ASSC21), Beijing, China. Metacognition of movement: the case of facial expressions.	
2014	Association for the Scientific Study of Consciousness (ASSC19), Brisbane, Australia. Lucid dreaming, introspection and awareness of mind-wandering: behavioural and brain bases	
	Organization for Human Brain Mapping (OHBM), Hamburg, Germany. Faces and houses perceived simultaneously in monocular rivalry images: fMRI evidence	
2012	Society for Neuroscience (SfN), New Orleans, USA. There is no free won't: antecedecent brain activity predicts decisions to inhibit	
	Association for the Scientific Study of Consciousness (ASSC16), Brighton, UK. Brain correlates of subjective freedom of choice	

2	\mathbf{a}	\sim	7
Z	u	u	/

Argentine Society for Neuroscience Research (SAN), Argentina. Coupling of the Type-L Voltage Dependent Calcium Channel to membrane endocytosis in the mouse neuromuscular junction.

("Estudio del acoplamiento del canal de calcio dependiente de voltaje de tipo L a la endocitosis de membrana en la unión neuromuscular de ratón.")

Workshops Led

2020	Running experiments online. 2.5 hours, Berlin School of Mind and Brain and Bernstein Center for Computational Neuroscience.
2019	Running web-based experiments in consciousness research. 3 hours, Association for the Scientific Study (ASSC23), London, Canada.
2018	Running experiments online with JATOS. 2.5 hours, MRC-Cognition and Brain Unit, Cambridge University, UK.
2016	Running experiments online with JATOS. 5 hours, Graduate School for Mind and Brain, Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin, Germany

Teaching

2019

Seminar series: Neural Bases of Metacognition. MSc, Berlin School of Mind and Brain. Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin. Course size: 9 students. Mean overall student rating: 5.11 (Minimum: 1 - Maximum: 6).

2018-2019

Contribution to lecture series. Neural bases of metacognition. MSc course "Models of Neural Systems", Bernstein Center for Computational Neuroscience. Course size: ca. 30 students. Latest mean overall student rating: 1.8 (Minimum: 5 - Maximum: 1).

Contribution to lecture series ("Ringvorlesung"). Neural bases of metacognition. BSc, Institute for Psychology, Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin.

2015-2016

Seminar Instructor, Sport Psychology. Leipzig University, Germany.

2010

Laboratory demonstrator, First year Psychology. University College London, UK.

Student Supervision

2017 - now	Supervision of PhD projects. Total to date (ongoing): 2
2018 - now	Secondary supervision of PhD projects. Total to date (ongoing): 3
2019 - now	Supervision of MSc theses projects. Total to date: 1
2018 - now	Supervision of 8-week rotation projects. Total to date: 7
2010 - 2011	Informal supervision of 3-months projects for an MSc in Neuroscience course. Total: 3

Ad-hoc Reviewing

2011-now Scientific Journals

Brain; Brain and Neuroscience Advances; Cognition; Cortex; Experimental Brain Research; Frontiers in Consciousness Research; Journal of Neurophysiology; Journal of Neuroscience; Neuroimage; Neuropsychologia; Neuroscience and Biobehavioural Reviews; PLoS one; Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences (PNAS); Psychology of Consciousness: Theory, Research, and Practice; Psychonomic Bulletin and Review; Scientific Reports; Social Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience (SCAN).

2019 Funding agencies

Wellcome Trust, UK

National Science Center Poland (NCN)

Klaus-Tschira Boost fund - German Scholars Organization

Other Contributions

2019 - now	Team leader in the Neural Architecture of Consciousness consortium. Metacognition Working Group. Approximately 15 active members (https://neuralarchcon.org/).
2019	Member of Scientific Committee – Association for the Scientific Study of Consciousness (ASSC)
20178 - now	Member of ProFiL Network. Professional network, training and coaching for women in natural and social sciences working in universities in Berlin.
2014 - now	Software development. Active development of an open-source software tool to run experiments online. www.jatos.org
2010-2012	F1000 - Comments and recommendations on scientific articles

Additional Professional Training

2018	Workshop series from Wissenschaftsmanagement (ZWM): "Professionals in
	Science". Included Communication and Conflict Management; Conducting
	Interviews; Research Project Management; Leadership.
2018	Workshop series from the ProFiL program (TU Berlin). Included Career
	Planning; Faculty Hiring Procedures in Germany and Abroad; Leadership;
	Academic Self-management: Writing Grant Applications

Public Engagement

2015	The Long Night of the Sciences. Berlin, Germany ("Lange Nacht der Wissenschaften") – Science outreach event.
2007	The Basement of Perception - Cognitive science outreach event. Museum of Natural History, Buenos Aires, Argentina.